Chicago, Ill. Iglesia Nueva Esperanza records, 1875-2007.
Congregational Library & Archives
Chicago, Ill. Iglesia Nueva Esperanza records, 1875-2007.
RG5344
Congregational Library & Archives
3.41 Cubic Feet
(5 boxes)
The Lawndale Congregational Church was formed in 1880. A church building was constructed in 1883. In 1889, the church changed its name to Millard Avenue Congregational Church. A significant fire damaged the church building in 1924. The church underwent renovations following the fire and again in 1934. Demographic shifts caused the church's membership to drop in the 1950s and 1960s. During the 1970s, the church became majority Hispanic and services and publications became bilingual. The church changed its name again in 1996 to Iglesia Nueva Esperanza. The church likely closed around 1999 or 2000. This collection includes meeting minutes and other church records, records of auxiliary groups, especially women's groups, runs of newsletters, event programs, vital membership records, and programmatic files.
Iglesia Nueva Esperanza (Chicago, Ill.)
Lawndale Congregational Church (Chicago, Ill.)
Millard Avenue Congregational Church (Chicago, Ill.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Chicago Theological Seminary in 2014; accession number 2014-124. Additional materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Illinois Conference of the United Church of Christ in December 2024; accession number 2024-46.
Custodial History
Some materials in this collection were given to the Illinois Conference of the United Church of Christ, likely around the time of the church's dissolution. There is no further documentation on how the materials arrived at the Illinois Conference.
Historical Note
In 1879, some families in the relatively sparsely populated area of Lawndale banded together to form an "Independent Ecclesiastical Society" and the following year they called a council to form the Lawndale Congregational Church. Construction on a church building at the intersection of 23rd and Central Park Avenue was completed in 1883. In 1889, the church changed its name to Millard Avenue Congregational Church.
On Christmas day, 1922, the church suffered a fire centered in the Sunday School rooms. The church was repaired and expanded following the fire. In 1934, the church once again underwent extensive renovations and refurbishing after it was discovered that the roof and foundation needed repair.
The Lawndale neighborhoods experienced significant white flight and disinvestment during the 1950s and 1960s. As a result, the Millard Avenue Congregational Church's membership declined and the church experienced financial hardship. In the 1970s, the church entered into a "Churches in Transition" covenant with the Community Renewal Society and Chicago Metropolitan Association. At the same time, the church was becoming predominantly Hispanic and began offering bilingual services and publications.
By the mid-1990s, the church changed its name to Iglesia Nueva Esperanza, and New Hope Church, in English. The church likely closed around 1999 or 2000; at the very least, the church last appears in the 1999 UCC yearbook. There are at least two churches in Chicago open today with the name Nueva Esperanza, however, it is unclear if either of these churches are successors or just similarly named.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains administrative records that document the operations of the Iglesia Nueva Esperanza, as well as records from auxiliary group, membership records and programmatic records which document the activities of the church and its members, and church publications. This collection includes meeting minutes for multiple administrative groups, financial records, women's club records, church newsletters, event programs, vital membership records, programmatic files, and service bulletins for special events and holidays.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into the four series listed below. Materials within each series have arranged into chronological order by start date.
Series 1: Church auxiliary records, 1875-1956
Series 2: Administrative records, 1879-1997
Series 3: Publications, 1890-1960
Series 4: Church membership and programs, 1911-1996
Baptismal records.; Church finance.; Church newsletters.; Church records and registers.; Marriage records.; Necrologies.; Women in church work.; Women -- Societies and clubs.; Worship programs.; Chicago (Ill.) -- Church history.; Community Renewal Society (Chicago, Ill.); Iglesia Nueva Esperanza (Chicago, Ill.); Lawndale Congregational Church (Chicago, Ill.); Millard Avenue Congregational Church (Chicago, Ill.)
- Church auxiliary records, 1875 1956; 1875-1956; 8 Volumes; 6 Folders; 43 Items
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records from church auxiliary groups. The majority of the records are from various iterations of the church's woman's groups, however, there are also records from the Friendship Circle and the Christian Endeavor group.
  - Ladies aid society records, 1875 1879; 1875-1879 (Box 1, Volume 10)
  - Ladies benevolent society financial records, 1901 1920; 1901-1920 (Box 1, Volume 11)
  - Millard Avenue woman's club directories, 1902 1954; 1902-1954 (Box 3, Item 1-42)
  - Woman's club realia, 1907 1929; 1907, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Christian Endeavor Society records, 1909 1923; 1909-1923 (Box 4, Volume 2)
  - Women's fellowship records, 1922 1949; 1922-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mothers' circle minutes, 1924 1927; 1924-1927 (Box 3, Volume 1)
  - Ladies guild financial records, 1926 1936; 1926, 1930-1936 (Box 1, Volume 12)
  - Ladies guild records, 1929 1932; 1929-1932 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Ladies guild records, 1933 1936; 1933-1936 (Box 1, Volume 14)
  - Past presidents of the woman's club records, 1935 1941; 1935-1941 (Box 1, Volume 13)
  - Friendship circle financial records, 1940 1946; 1940-1946 (Box 1, Volume 15)
  - Friendship circle records, 1942 1946; 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Women's fellowship information book, 1948 1952; 1948-1952 (Box 3, Volume 2)
  - Woman's club monthly bulletin, 1954 1956; 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Woman's club constitution, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Administrative records, 1879 1997; 1879-1997; 14 Volumes; 26 Folders
  This series contains records related broadly to the administration of the church and operation of the church's physical space. This series include church records, trustee records, council records, ledgers and other financial records, property and tax related records, meeting minutes, and governance documents. Church records volumes often contain both administrative records and membership records.
  - Society records, 1879 1912; 1879-1912 (Box 4, Volume 1)
  - Trustees records, 1891 1899; 1891-1899 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Reports, 1891 1921; 1891, 1915-1921 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Ledger, 1900 1941; 1900-1941 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Clerks records, 1909 1915; 1909-1915 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Financial records, 1912 1914; 1912-1914 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - Board of trustees records, 1912 1930; 1912-1930 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Society records, 1914 1922; 1914-1922 (Box 4, Volume 3)
    Separated Materials
    Loose materials in this volume were removed and placed in the folder labeled "Miscellaneous society records, 1917-1923." This was done primarily for the long-term preservation of those materials.
  - Miscellaneous society records, 1917 1923; 1917-1923 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Materials in this folder were removed from the volume titled "Society records, 1914-1922." This was done to support the long-term preservation of these materials.
  - Church records, 1919 1940; 1919-1940 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  - Church records, 1919 2007; 1919-2007 (Box 1, Volume 5)
  - Financial records, 1932 1942; 1932-1942 (Box 5, Volume 1)
  - Building committee records, 1934 (Box 1, Volume 6)
  - By-law revisions, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Financial records, 1936 1950; 1936-1950 (Box 4, Volume 4)
  - Board of trustees records, 1937 1946; 1937-1946 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Church council meeting minutes, 1941 1954; 1941-1954 (Box 1, Volume 7)
  - Board of trustees records, 1946 1950; 1946-1950 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Deacon's board records, 1946 1971; 1946-1971 (Box 5, Volume 2)
  - Board of trustees records, 1953 1959; 1953-1959 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Church records, 1954 1967; 1954-1967 (Box 1, Volume 8)
  - Miscellaneous reports, 1958 1994; 1958-1994 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Janitor instructions, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Board of trustees records, 1960 1965; 1960-1965 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Church records, 1967 1981; 1967-1981 (Box 1, Volume 9)
  - Miscellaneous reports, communications, and church records, 1970 1979; 1970-1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Every Member Canvass committee records, 1972 1978; 1972-1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Property tax exemption, 1972 1990; 1972-1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Renovation proposals and estimates, 1974 1975; 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Board of trustees correspondence, 1974 1976; 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Deacon, pastoral, council, and trustee records, 1983 1985; 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Lawndale Avenue property purchase loan records, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous meeting minutes, 1990 1996; 1990-1996 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Mortgage foreclosure legal records, circa 1993 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous financial records, 1995 1997; 1995-1997 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous records, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Constitution, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Statement of faith, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Floor plans, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Publications, 1890 1960; 1890-1960; 8 Folders
  This series contains print materials published by and for the church and its community. The majority of the records in this series are newsletters however the series also contains directories and a church manual.
  - Church manual, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Millard Ave. Congregational Herald, 1923 1930; 1923-1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Directories, 1926 1928; 1926-1928 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Millard Outlook, 1932 1933; 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Millard Outlook, 1938 1940; 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Millard Outlook, 1941 1942; 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Millard Outlook, 1943 1947; 1943-1947 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - The Outlook, 1957 1960; 1957-1960 (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Church membership and programs, 1911 1996; 1911-1996; 2 Volumes; 27 Folders
  This series contains records related to the church's membership as well as programs the church both ran and participated in. This series includes church histories, membership records, such as baptismal records, event and service programs, youth program records, photographs, and guest books.
  - Church history, 1911 1978; circa 1911, 1934-1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Guest book, 1934 1952; 1934-1952 (Box 1, Volume 16)
  - Pastor report, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Anniversary celebrations, 1934 1993; 1934-1993 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Histories, 1942 1979; 1942, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Baptism records, 1944 1947; 1944-1947 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1956 1996; 1956, 1965-1996 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Churches in transitions covenant, 1971 1980; 1971-1980 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Music program, 1974 1976; 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Pastoral reports, 1977 1981; 1977-1981 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Membership records, 1978 1979; 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Summer youth program photo album, 1978 1979; 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Guest book, 1979 1980; 1979-1980 (Box 1, Volume 17)
  - Casa de la Cultura "Millard" records, 1979 1980; 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Youth party photographs, 1979 1980; 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Programs and activities photo album, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Christmas children lists, 1982 1983; 1982-1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Thanksgiving services, 1983 1989; 1983-1989 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Miscellaneous membership records, 1984 1985; 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Christmas season programs, 1984 1991; 1984-1991 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Miscellaneous Sunday programs, 1985 1988; 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Church and community project, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Little Village Resource Center lease, 1988 1990; 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Certificates, 1988 1993; 1988, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Board of Metropolitan Mission records, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Miscellaneous programs and flyers, 1994 1996; 1994-1996 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - TV Christmas Story script, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Ceremony of ordinations, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Miscellaneous photographic materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)